Senjougahara Hitagi
Sen        jou       gahara
No group
もしもし 戦場ヶ原
Hey, Senjougahara.
どうしたの?
End Story
What is it?
こうして電話をかけてきたということは
このたびのトラブルはもう解決したの?
I assume the problems you had earlier are resolved if you're calling me now.
まだ終わってないんだけど
Not really.
ごめん
Sorry.
我慢しきれなかった
I just had to call you.
心細くって
I felt alone.
I see.
そう
まあ 羽川さんのことはこちらに任せておいて
Well, I'll take care of Hanekawa.
羽川に何かあったのか?
What happened to her?
神原から聞いていない?
Kanbaru didn't tell you?
Tell me what?
何を?
まあ 聞いていないのなら 帰って来てから
本人から直接聞けばいいわ
Just ask Hanekawa yourself once she's home, I guess.
なあ 戦場ヶ原
Hey, Senjougahara.
There's something I want to know.
一個 教えて欲しいことがあるんだけれど
一年前 神原が直江津高校に入学してきて
お前に会いに来たとき
One year ago, when Kanbaru transferred into Naoetsu High School to see you...
正直なところ どう思った?
What did you think of it?
Well...
そうね
正直 重いって思ったわね
Frankly, I thought it was a bit of a burden.
あの子の気持ちは
The strength of her feelings, I mean.
けれど それは あの子の重さに耐え切れない
私の軽さの表れでもあったでしょうね
Conversely, you can think of it as proof that I was too shallow to appreciate her back then.
私が神原と一緒にいたいのであれば
その重さに耐えられる自分でなければならなかったのでしょう
Being with her would have required me to be a better person.
今だって そう思いながら研鑽(けんさん)中よ
I'm working on that, even now.
I still labor away
努力しているのよ これでも
阿良々木くんのお嫁(よめ)さんになるために
to become worthy enough to be your bride.
Senjougahara Hitagi
Sen        jou       gahara
No group
Is that a burden for you?
重い?
いえ 決してそういうわけでは
No, not at all.
Purity in Spirit
これが最後かもしれねーから お前が怒るかもしれないこと
訊いていいか?
This might be our last chance, so can I ask you something that might upset you?
Senjougahara Hitagi
Sen        jou       gahara
No group
僕よりも条件のいい奴がお前に告白してきたら
そのとき どうする?
What would you do if someone confessed to you who was a better match than me?
I'd switch to him ten times out of ten.
そのときは百パーセント乗り換えると思う
すげえな お前
You're amazing...
それが言えるってすげえな
Amazingly blunt.
絆に絶対なんてないことを
私は知っている
There are no absolutes in human relationships.
I learned that from watching my parents.
両親を見て 学んでいる
戦場ヶ原 いや それは
Senjougahara, what I meant was—
I'm actually a little scared when I try to imagine an unconditional bond.
絶対的な絆なんて
考えてみたら結構怖いしね
だから乗り換えられないよう
努力しなさいという話でしょ
I suggest you take this as encouragement to work on yourself so that I won't think of leaving.
特別な人間にはなれなくとも
誰かの特別にはなれるでしょ
You will never be special, but you can be special in the eyes of someone else.
誰かの 特別
Special in the eyes of someone else...
Senjougahara Hitagi
Sen        jou       gahara
No group
私は神原や阿良々木くんにとって特別な人間であろうと
絶え間なく努力している
I toil incessantly to be special in the eyes of you and Kanbaru.
安心しなさい 阿良々木くん
Don't be afraid, Araragi.
あなたは十分 特別な人間よ
You are special
私にとっても 神原にとっても
in my eyes and Kanbaru's.
忍ちゃんにとっても
In Shinobu's too.
私達はあなたを選んでいる
We chose you.
本当に理解していたのか...
You realized what I was getting at.
すげえな
Amazing.
Senjougahara Hitagi
Sen        jou       gahara
No group
彼女ですから
I'm your girlfriend.
電話してきてくれたこと とても嬉しかったわ
I'm very happy you called me.
愛してる
I love you.
帰ったら もうちょっと...
When I get home, let us...
もっと こういう話をしよう
Let us talk more about this.
Senjougahara Hitagi
Sen        jou       gahara
No group
Yes.
裸で待ってるわ
I'll be waiting for you naked.
神原の変態って お前の影響強いよな?
Kanbaru is really taking after you, huh?
End Story
Shinobu Mail Part Six
じゃ ちゃっちゃと始めてちゃっちゃと終わらそうか
Let's get started and get this over with.
おいで
Come here.
はい これでよし
That should do it.
準備完了
We're all set up.
これで阿良々木くんも 臨戦態勢だね
Araragi should be ready for battle as well.
準備完了?
All set up? That?
それで準備完了?
おいおい しばし待たれよ
Please do wait.
ペアリングはどうしたのでござる? 阿良々木殿
What about the link, Sir Araragi?
まさかそんな弱いままで
拙者と決闘する気ではなかろうな?
Surely you do not intend to fight me as weak as you are.
He no longer had the voice he took from me.
He had his own back.
It seems your bond with Kiss-Shot is not as strong as I feared.
やれやれ どうやら拙者が心配していたほどに
おぬしとキスショットとの絆は強くないようでござる
I can't believe she would send her servant to battle in such a state.
従僕をそんな弱いままで 戦場に送り出すなど
信じられぬ
I don't want to win using Shinobu's help.
僕は 忍の力で勝ちたいんじゃない
勝って 忍の力になりたいのだ
I want to win and help her.
まあよかろう
Well, all right.
だが伊豆湖殿 こうなると
ちゃんとハンディキャッピングをした上での決闘法を設けて欲しいものでござるよ
Lady Izuko, please think of a way to handicap me for this duel.
聞き苦しい言い訳はごめんじゃ
I will not abide any excuses.
もちろん
No problem.
古来より伝わる
普遍的な決闘法を採用するつもりだ
We will use a handicap well-employed throughout the ages.
それなりに きみ達が公平に競えるようにね
You two should be on an even footing.
仮想 妖刀"心渡"と言ったところかな
This is something like a virtual version of the demon sword Heart Span.
もちろん 霊気を通してある
Of course, it does channel power.
うん まあ
互いに有効なスタンガンみたいなものだと思ってくれ
It will easily stun either of you.
まずはきみ達には この竹刀を挟んで
背中合わせに立ってもらう
Please stand back-to-back now,
with the bamboo sword between you.
そして私のカウントに合わせて
そこから十歩 前方に向かって歩く
I will count to ten and you will
take a step forward each time.
十歩目を最後に バトル開始だ
On the tenth step, the duel begins.
この竹刀に駆け寄って
相手に一太刀(ひとたち)浴びせたほうの勝ち
The winner will be whoever whacks the other with the sword here.
もちろん 相手から竹刀を奪い取って
一撃を入れてもいい
If you can take the sword from your opponent and hit him, that's fine too.
あくまでも勝負の基準は"一太刀勝負"だ
What wins the duel is hitting the opponent once.
要するに
So, essentially,
状況を公平にするというより 阿良々木殿が
決闘で死なないようにするための気遣いというわけじゃな
your goal is not to make this fair, but to keep Araragi from dying.
よく考えるものでござる
You plan ahead.
他に質問は?
Any other questions?
No, ma'am.
ない
阿良々木くんから質問は?
And you, Araragi?
僕は剣も戦いも素人なんで
Seeing as how I'm a novice to swordsmanship and combat,
せめて その十歩分のランについて
専門家から教えを受けてもいいですか?
can I at least be taught the best way
to run those ten steps by a specialist?
専門家?
By a specialist?
オッケー
Sure.
それくらいのハンデは 追加してもいいだろう
I'm fine with adding that condition.
じゃあ今が七時半だから...
It's seven thirty right now, so...
Let's start at eight on the dot.
八時ジャストに 決闘開始だ
ご両所とも
Combatants,
ウォーミングアップに励んでくれたまえ
please commence your warm-up routine.
身長から推察するに
阿良々木先輩の歩幅は約七十二センチ
I'd estimate based on your height that you have a seventy-two centimeter stride.
つまり十歩分なら 七メートル二十センチだ
Basically, seven meters, twenty centimeters after ten steps.
マラソンにはマラソンの戦略が
百メートル走には百メートル走の戦略があるように
Just as there are different strategies for marathons and one-hundred meter sprints,
there are strategies for seven meter sprints too.
七メートルを走るには
七メートルを走る戦略がある
ただ この場合は余力の残しかたが課題かもしれない
I think the problem will be how to conserve your energy.
課題って?
Problem?
走り切ってそれで終わりではないということだ
Just running there with all you've got isn't everything.
竹刀をつかんで 一太刀入れなければいけないのだろう?
You still have to hit him once with the sword.
Right.
ああ そっか
重要なのは結局
竹刀を取ったあとのチャンバラのほうだと思うぞ
The important part of it is the fracas once you've grabbed the sword.
阿良々木先輩が竹刀をとっても 一撃をかわされ 竹刀を奪われ
その後叩きのめされては 折角の努力も水の泡だろう
It would be a pity if he dodged your blow, stole the sword, and beat you up with it.
そうだが まあ
Uh, yeah, but...
それはなるようになるとしか言えないだろう
You can't really plan for that.
そこまでお前を煩わすわけにはいかない
I don't want to drag you into it.
じゃあせめて 私のシューズを貸そうか
All right. Will you at least borrow my shoes?
サイズは同じだろう
We have the same size.
ああ ありがとう
Thanks.
何これ?
What the hell?
ぼ 僕がしばらく学校に来ていない間に
何があったんだ...?
What happened while I was skipping school?
神原 お前 何か知っているか?
Do you have an idea?
いや 私にもさっぱりわからないが...
No, I don't...
Hanekawa was made homeless by fire,
家が火事になって焼け出された羽川先輩が
戦場ヶ原先輩の紹介を経て 火憐ちゃんや月火ちゃんを頼る形で
阿良々木先輩の家に滞在している
and through Senjougahara's mediation she's been staying with Karen and Tsukihi at your house.
くらいしか思いつかない
That's about all I can think of.
Well, that's probably it!
たぶんそれ正解だろ!
Hold on! Fire?
って 火事!?
Homeless?
焼け出された!?
What?
何の話だよ それ!
Looks like she's heading for the climax.
おやおや あっちはあっちで佳境(かきょう)のようだねえ
What will you do, Koyomin?
どうする こよみん?
Do you know something, Izuko?
伊豆湖さん 何か知っているんですか?
羽川が—
Is Hanekawa—
いや そもそも羽川を知っているんですか?
I mean, do you know Hanekawa?
それに どうするって...
Also, what do you mean? What will I do?
何を
私は何でも知っている
I know everything.
だから虎だよ こよみん
It's a tiger, Koyomin.
きみを学習塾跡で
皮肉にも救った虎だけれど
The same tiger who ironically saved you in the cram school.
It looks like Tsubasa has resolved to face the large tiger that controls the flames of purgatory.
煉獄(れんごく)の炎を司(つかさど)るその大虎と 翼ちゃんは
向き合う決心をしたらしい
It's not just Tsubasa who's in trouble.
ピンチなのは実のところ
翼ちゃんだけじゃない
きみの彼女の戦場ヶ原さんも
同じくピンチだ
Your girlfriend Senjougahara is facing the same troubles.
何?
What?
They might already be burning bright as we speak.
ひょっとすると こうしている今にも彼女達は
燃え盛っているかもしれない
助けに行くなら 一刻も早く
今すぐにでも行ったほうがいい
If you want to help them, you should go as soon as possible.
こんな さして
やる意味のない決闘を放棄してね
Abandon this pointless duel.
I would really like for you to forfeit.
きみが決闘してくれないほうが
私としては助かるんだ
きみに死なれたら困るからね
It would be a problem if you died on me.
私からルールを破るわけにはいかないから
きみが自らルールを破ってくれると とても助かるのさ
I can't break the rules myself, so you must do it.
こよみんもよかったじゃないか
Isn't this perfect for you too?
決闘を取りやめる絶好の理由ができて
It gives you a plausible reason to stop this duel.
選ぶんだね こよみん
Choose, Koyomin.
無為(むい)な決闘をするためにこのままここに留まるのか
Will you stay here for your futile duel?
Naoetsu Private High School
Will you run to Tsubasa's and Senjougahara's aid?
翼ちゃんと戦場ヶ原さんを助けるために走り出すのか
Will you choose Shinobu?
忍ちゃんを選ぶのか
Will you choose Tsubasa?
翼ちゃんを選ぶのか
Will you choose Senjougahara?
戦場ヶ原さんを選ぶのか
三人の中で 誰が一番好きなんだい?
Which of the three do you like most?
神原 頼む
Kanbaru, listen.
頼まれた
I'll do it!
阿良々木先輩の家に行けばいいんだな?
You want me to run to your house, right?
火憐に言って家に入れてもらってくれ
Get Karen to let you in.
すぐに追いつくから
I'll be there soon.
先に調べておいて欲しい
Look through Tsubasa's things for me.
Orders received.
委細承知
正気かい?
Are you quite sane?
考えられないよ
It's unbelievable.
きみは 本当に目の前のことしか見えないのかい?
You really see only what's in front of you.
確かに きみよりよっぽど機動力のある
神原駿河さんに走らせれば
It's true that you might be able to respond to both situations if you send Kanbaru,
どちらにも対応できるかもしれない
since she's a lot faster than you.
Tsubasa might even be able to handle it alone.
翼ちゃんなら 自力で
困難に立ち向かうかもしれない
ここで戦えるのはきみだけなんだから
Since you are the only combatant here, being the only one to stay behind might be the correct decision.
きみがここに残るのは正しいかもしれない
だけど そんなのは理屈だ
But that's just theory.
人には感情がある
People have feelings.
きみを信じて
彼女はメールを送ってきてくれたんじゃないのかな
It looks to me like she sent you that text hoping you'd come.
その信頼を裏切るのかい?
Will you betray her trust?
この裏切りで きみは二度と
彼女達から信用してもらえなくなるんじゃないのかい?
They will never trust you again if you betray them now.
That may be.
そうかもしれない
But I should trust them.
だけど 僕があいつらを信じている
羽川のことを 戦場ヶ原のことを
心から信じている
I trust Hanekawa and Senjougahara from the bottom of my heart.
They are special to me, and will understand.
Hanekawa Tsubasa and
Senjougahara Hitagi will understand.
阿良々木暦という男が 恩人や恋人よりも
時に幼女を優先する男だと わかってくれると信じている
I trust that they understand that the man Araragi Koyomi prioritizes little girls over lovers and friends.
携帯電話をまるごと預けられるような感触で
いつか私も人を信じてみたいものだ
One day, I would like to trust others enough to give them my cell phone.
超ウケる
That's hilarious.
奴隷同士の争いに
主人として道具立てくらいは用意しようってかい
Is your master delivering your tools?
いや この場合は景品か?
Or is this the winner's prize?
勝ったほうが妖刀を授与されるとか よ
The winner gets the demon sword or something.
かもね
Perhaps.
いずれにしても
私が折角用意した竹刀は真っ二つだし
Either way, the bamboo sword I prepared has been split cleanly in two.
You'll have to use the real one.
本物を使うしかない
こよみん 初代くん
Koyomin, First One.
時間を少々過ぎてしまったが
始めてもらおうか
We have tarried, but let us begin now.
Do as arranged and stand back-to-back next to the sword.
予定通り その刀を間に
背中合わせになっておくれ
すぐそばまで来ておきながら どうして我があるじ
キスショットは姿を見せぬ?
She is clearly close, and yet my master, Kiss-Shot, does not show herself.
そんなに キスショットは
拙者に会いたくないのかのう
Is she that reluctant to meet me?
阿良々木殿 どう思う?
What do you think, Sir Araragi?
拙者とおぬしとのいざこざは キスショットにとっては
心底 迷惑なだけなのかのう?
Is our quarrel, in the end, a grievance to her?
おぬしにとっては 阿良々木殿
この決闘はどういう意味を持つ?
What does this duel mean to you, Sir Araragi?
僕にとっての意味は
お前にはわからないよ
You wouldn't understand what it means to me.
お前は特別で
選ばれた人間なのかもしれない
You are special, a chosen being.
僕は特別じゃないし
選ばれてないかもしれない
Perhaps I'm not special or chosen.
お前の代わりは誰にもできなくて
Nobody can replace you,
僕の代わりは誰にでもできるのかもしれない
and perhaps anybody could replace me.
だけどな
But, you know.
You can never be me.
お前は僕にはなれないよ
Countless could replace me,
僕の代わりはいくらでもいるけれど
but there is only one me.
僕は僕しかいないから
You are not me,
お前は僕じゃないし
僕はお前じゃない
and I am not you.
そういうことだろ?
Isn't that all there is to it?
One
One.
いーち
Two
Two.
Three
Three.
さーん
Four
Four.
よーん
Five.
Five
Six.
Six
ろく
Seven.
Seven
Eight
Eight.
はーち
Nine.
Nine
きゅう
Ten.
じゅう!
メメの...
That's Meme's...
ああ そういうことか
Oh, I see.
驚いた
Count me surprised.
これは本当に想定外だ
This is very unexpected.
まさか一太刀浴びせたら勝ちという私の設定したルールを
ひとタッチ浴びせたら勝ちだと曲解してくるだなんて!
This was certainly not what I meant when I said you had to hit the other once to win.
キスショット...
キスショット キスショット
Kiss-Shot...
Crab
Snail
Monkey
Snake
Cat
Bee
Phoenix
Tiger
Dog
Bear
Leopard
Ladybug
Zebra
Fox
Coral
Camel
Sea Cucumber
Cow
Lion
Giraffe
Crayfish
Shark
Ostrich
Wolf
Turtle
Deer
Goat
Chicken
Rabbit
Millipede
Mold
Raccoon
Lizard
Spider
Mole
Silkworm
Squirrel
Whale
Octopus
Dugong
Rhinoceros Beetle
Otter
Crane
Turban Shell
Inchworm
Tadpole
Anteater
Flying Squirrel
Scorpion
Narwhal
Earthworm
Walking Stick
Swan
Oyster
Elephant
Carp
Llama
Sea Otter
Mushroom
Sheep
Crocodile
Cicada
Rhinoceros
Sea Urchin
Rat
Sea Horse
Parrot
Balloonfish
Reindeer
Flounder
Pangolin
Jellyfish
Peafowl
Praying Mantis
Kiss-Shot...
キスショット...
I don't know how long I will end up living.
まあ... 僕がいったい何歳まで
生きられるのかわかんないけど
But if we can meet again during my life...
生きているうちに また会えたら
また会えたら
If we can meet again,
また会おう
then let us meet.
Don't apologize.
謝らんでもよい
許した
I forgive you.
儂のほうこそ悪かった
I'm sorry too,
Seishirou.
生死郎(せいしろう)
Naoetsu Private High School
会えて嬉しかった
I'm glad I met you again.
もう会えないと思ってたから
I thought I'd never see you again.
だけどもう会わない
But now we will never meet again.
今の儂には
うぬより大事な者がおる
There's someone who's more important to me than you now.
今しばらくは
そやつのための儂でいたい
I want to be there for him for a while.
さっぱりせず 気持ちよくもなく はっきり言ってくれたほうが
却(かえ)って楽にもならず これといった救いもなく
Four hundred years after the first attempt, his suicide was finally successful,
Naoetsu Private High School
without a fulfilling conclusion,
without providing relief through honesty,
だけども それでも
実行から四百年の時を経て
彼の自殺は
ようやく成功したのだった
and without any kind of salvation.
Yes, very interesting.
それでそれからどうなったんですか
阿良々木先輩?
And what happened then, Araragi?
後日談と言うか 今回のオチは
What about the epilogue? The outcome?
そのあとは もう前に話した通りだよ
The rest was told elsewhere.
先行して僕の家に向かってくれた神原と合流して
羽川の虎の件に合流した
I rendezvoused with my vanguard Kanbaru and met with Hanekawa and the tiger.
Reference
I went to Hanekawa and Kanbaru went to Senjougahara.
僕は羽川の下に向かい
神原は戦場ヶ原の下へと向かった
そうですかそうですか
I see, I see.
いや ありがとうございました
阿良々木先輩
Thank you very much, Araragi.
これでパズルのピースが
すべて埋まりましたよ
Now the puzzle has been filled in.
これまで聞いていた話と
若干細部が矛盾する箇所もありますけれど
A few small parts contradict each other,
そういう矛盾の辻褄合わせも あらゆる物語の聞き手こと私
忍野扇の楽しみでもあります
but making those coherent is part of what I enjoy as a listener.
Koyo
mist
March 13th (Tue)
本日は 三月十三日
Today is the 13th of March.
March 13th (Tue)
Date of Exam:
General Entrance Exams
僕の受験本番当日の 早朝だった
Later today I'll be taking my entrance exams.
じゃ 今日はもう帰りますね
I'll be going, then.
生きていれば またお会いしましょう
Let's meet again if we're still alive.
あと一点
One more thing.
忍さんは 一人目の眷属を 結局のところ
食べ切ったんですか?
Did Shinobu eat her first kin in his entirety?
いや... それはそう言ったろ?
Uh, didn't I say that?
食べ残しなく?
Without leaving anything behind?
ああ 食べ残しなく
Without leaving anything behind.
What about the armor?
甲冑も?
1     2     3     4     5     6     7     8
食べた... と思う
She ate it... I think.
かもしれない
Maybe.
But...
けれど...
それが 何か重要なのかい?
Is that important?
だって その鎧もまた 初代怪異殺しの"血肉"であり
"骨身"でしょう?
Well, the armor is part of his flesh and blood, his bones.
だったら その鎧をどろどろに溶かして そしてその上で鍛造(たんぞう)すれば
更にもう一振り 作れるかもしれないじゃあないですか 妖刀"心渡"が
If you melt it down, you can reforge it as another demon sword Heart Span.
In fact, ideally, as the short sword Dream Span.
どころか あわよくば
小太刀(こだち) "夢渡(ゆめわたり)"も
"夢渡"?
Dream Span?
私がもしも臥煙さんだったら 忍さんに食べられてしまう前に
鎧は回収するでしょうね
If I were Gaen, I would collect the armor, lest Shinobu eat it.
案外 エピソードくんは
そのために呼ばれたのかもしれませんねえ
Maybe that's the real reason she called Episode.
She has no reason to do that.
臥煙さんがそんなことをする理由がないだろ
僕は普通に 甲冑も忍が食べたんだと思うぜ
I think Shinobu ate it at some point.
うん 確かそうだった気がする
I think that's what happened.
Then let me answer one of your questions too.
では 私のほうからもひとつだけ
阿良々木先輩の疑問にお答えしておきましょう
僕の疑問?
My questions? Which are?
僕の疑問って 何?
死屍累(ししるい)生死郎
Shishirui Seishirou.
Shishirui Seishirou
それが初代怪異殺しのフルネームです
That's the full name of the first oddity slayer.
阿良々木先輩も やっぱり恋敵の名前は
ちゃんと認識しておきたいでしょう?
Wouldn't you want to know the name of your rival in love?
話は偶然聞かせてもらったよ
I happened to overhear your conversation.
Again?
またかよ
Don't worry.
I avoided contact with her.
I clung to the ceiling
as she passed underneath.
鬼いちゃん あの子にはなんだか緩いよね
You're very soft on her, aren't you?
口 軽過ぎない?
Don't you tell her too much?
そうか?
Really?
別にそんなことないと思うぜ?
I don't think so.
鬼いちゃんがいいなら
それでいいんだけどね
If you say so.
今から北白蛇神社に行くつもりなんだけど
I was on my way to the Shrine of the Polar Snake.
一緒にどう?
Want to tag along?
どこだいそれ?
Where's that?
忘れてんじゃねえよ
Don't forget it.
色々忘れ過ぎだろ きみは
You forget too much.
きみのご主人が行方不明になった場所だよ
It's where your master went missing.
鬼いちゃんと朝デートなんてしない
It's too early in the morning for a date with you.
ただ それで言うなら
僕にも教えて欲しいことがある
But I have a question for you too.
なんだい?
Which is?
Are you happy that you became a vampire?
鬼いちゃん 吸血鬼になって
幸せ?
初代怪異殺しが
そんなことを言っていたじゃない
Didn't the first oddity slayer talk about that?
鬼いちゃんが忍先生と共にあることで
俺にどんないいことがあるのかって
Didn't he ask you whether there was a good reason for him to let you stay with her?
You weren't able to give him a
good reason to stay with her then,
結局 その場で鬼いちゃんは
彼にとってのメリットを提示することはできなかったわけだけれども
その気持ちは今でも変わらない?
but maybe that has changed.
Do you still believe nobody is made happier if you are with Shinobu?
鬼いちゃんが忍先生と共にあることで
誰も幸せになっていないと 今も思ってる?
今も思ってる
I still think so.
誰も幸せにならないし
Nobody becomes happy.
誰も幸せになれない
Nobody can become happy.
僕が吸血鬼であることで 僕が忍と一緒にいることで
みんなに迷惑しかかけられない
If I am a vampire, if I am with Shinobu, it only imposes a burden on others.
誰よりも 忍を不幸にしてしまっている
Shinobu most of all.
言い訳のようにも聞こえるけれどね
That sounds like excuses to me.
幸せにならないから勘弁してください 幸せになろうとなんかしないから
どうか許してください どうか見逃してくださいと言っているようにも
It sounds to me like you're telling me to leave you alone because you won't be happy and aren't trying to be.
僕達はこんなに不幸なんだから責めるなよ
可哀想だろって主張しているようにも
It sounds like you're pleading for sympathy because of your own misfortune.
ねえ鬼いちゃん
You know...
ひょっとしてあなた 不幸や不遇に甘んじていることを
"頑張ってる"と思っちゃってるんじゃないの?
Are you one of those people who think wallowing in unhappiness and bad luck is the same as toughing it out?
Most people just call it "apathy."
そういうのを世間では
"何もしていない"って言うんだよ
不幸なくらいで許されると思うな
Misfortune isn't a valid excuse.
ハッピーエンドを目指すべきだ
You have to shoot for the happy ending.
また顔を踏んであげようか?
Shall I step on your face again?
厳しいなあ 斧乃木ちゃんは
You're so hard on me, Ononoki.
不幸でい続けることは怠慢だし
Languishing in unhappiness is simply negligence.
幸せになろうとしないことは卑怯だよ
Not trying to be happy is for cowards.
そんなんじゃ自殺した先駆者も報われまい
It won't redeem your dead predecessor either.
I'll remember that.
聞いておくよ
誰も幸せになっていない
Nobody is happy.
Not me.
僕も
忍も
Not Shinobu.
誰一人
No one.
For now, that's what I think—
That's what I still think.
だけどひょっとしたら今よりもずっと先
遥か遥か未来
But perhaps, a long time from now,
たとえば四百年後とかには
その考えかたも少しは変わっているかもしれないと そんなことを思いながら
maybe about four hundred years,
my thoughts on the matter could change.
Stop
なあに 幸せではなくとも幸いなことに
時間はまだまだ腐るほどある
I may not be happy, but happily enough we still have much time.
時間だけは 考える時間も生きる時間も
うんざりするほど
Time to live, time to think.
Beware
of
Rail
Crossing
Enough time for corpses to rot away and turn into dust.
死体が腐って灰になるくらい
僕達にはあるのだ
だけどそんな時間がなくなるのも
あるいは時間の問題なのかもしれなかった
That this time would come to an end was, perhaps, only a matter of time as well.
I hear your laughter beyond the door
You were supposed to be with me forever
I breathed onto the classroom window and wrote your name
only to panic and wipe it with my sleeve
I heard your voice from the hallway
and went home in hurry to hide my feelings
At some point I became unable
to talk to you normally
I can hear your laughter beyond the door
You were supposed to be next to me forever
You knew how I felt
even when I said nothing
Now I know how important you were to me,
but we will never see each other again